<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons The former discouering a double and false heart, vpon the I. King. 21. 9. and 10. The second called, the blessednes of the righteous, vpon Psalm. 37. verse 37. The third, the court of guard, or watch of angels: I, Sam. 17. 37. By Nathaniel Cannon, Preacher of Gods Word at Hurley in Berkeshire.</title>
            <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852289</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852289</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17605</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17605)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1130:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons The former discouering a double and false heart, vpon the I. King. 21. 9. and 10. The second called, the blessednes of the righteous, vpon Psalm. 37. verse 37. The third, the court of guard, or watch of angels: I, Sam. 17. 37. By Nathaniel Cannon, Preacher of Gods Word at Hurley in Berkeshire.</title>
                  <author>Cannon, Nathanael, 1581 or 2-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 53 [i.e. 61], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. C[reede] and B. A[lsop] for William Welby, and are to be sold in Pauls Church yard, at the signe of the Swan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Page 61 misnumbered 53.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A double heart.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed? Includes first sermon only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17605:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17605:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS: THE FORMER DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVERING A DOVBLE and falſe Heart, vpon the 1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.9. <hi>and</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>THE SECOND CALLED, THE BLESSEDNES OF the Righteous, vpon Pſalm. 37. verſe 37.</p>
            <p>THE THIRD, THE COVRT of Guard, or Watch of Angels: 1. Sam. 17.37.</p>
            <p>Nathaniel Cannon, <hi>Preacher of Gods Word at Hurley in Berkeſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T.C.</hi> and <hi>B.A.</hi> for <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls Church yard, at the Signe of the Swan. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17605:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17605:2"/>
            <head>TO THE THRISE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED PEERE, MY LORDS Grace, the Duke of <hi>Lennox,</hi> Earle of Richmont, Lord High Steward of his Maieſties Houſhould, Knight of the moſt noble and illuſtrious Order of the Garter, and one of his Maieſties moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Priuie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it may become a Seruant, to make ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his dutie vnto his Lord and Maſter, then may your Grace vouchſafe to patronage this poore
<pb facs="tcp:17605:3"/>preſent, notwithſtanding, it comes thus meanely apparelled. My offering is but little, and leſſe then euer was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſo great a perſonage: yet let it not periſh, but find ſuch acceptation, as may giue teſtimonie of your moſt heroicall diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>When firſt I had leaue to call you Lord, it was in my heart to doe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but neuer had the heart till now, &amp; now too ſoone, for I may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge to your Grace, that this <hi>hoc aliquid nihil eſt,</hi> this is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſomething nothing, that is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>And yet great Lord, I doe not, nor I dare not, ſpeake meanely of my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: but my gifts, with ioy, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and I hope with conſcience, I may ioyne with our Apoſtles ſaying, that I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> becauſe it is the power of God vnto ſaluation, to euery one that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: ſo that in this reſpect, although
<pb facs="tcp:17605:3"/>the Lord hath made you great, yet if you were greater, and the greateſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth, yet know it is the word of God, of that glorious God, who is the Creator, and the Kings and Princes, Dukes and Nobles are but his creatures as other men: <hi>vos eſtis domini terrae:</hi> indeed you are the Lords of the earth,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 82.1.</note> and yet your ſelues are but <hi>(Terra domini)</hi> euen the earth of the Lords, as other men.</p>
            <p>O therefore let a ſeruant ſpeake, if you would double and trebble Honors vpon your head, let the Word of God be the lanthorne vnto your feete, and the light vnto your pathes,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.</note> you ſhall ſee the way that leades vnto life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting: <hi>verbum eſt via,</hi> the Word is the way: <hi>haec via ducit ad vrbem,</hi> this way leades vnto the hauen: yea vnto the heauen prepared for thoſe that loue, that heare, that reuerence and obey this word of God, there ſhall you cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge your Dukedome for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for he crownes his children.
<note place="margin">Reuel. 5.10.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17605:4"/>
            <p> If then the eminent Lords would raiſe their houſes, let them raiſe vp their hearts, and ſet them vpon righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, for them, ſaith God, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me, I will honour them, but they that neglect, or deſpiſe the Lord, ſhall downe to the ground.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed therefore moſt Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30</note> in reſpect of him whoſe word it is, to looke vpon this ſmall Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although in reſpect both of my weakeneſſe and vnworthineſſe that doe preſent, it may fall to the ground.
<note place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Artax.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Be vnto me in this kind a Princely <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> he receiued a handful of running water from a poore laborer, be as gratious noble Lord, in receiuing this from me a poore Scholler, whileſt I according to my beu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den duty, pray to my God for your increaſe of honor and happines, internall, externall, eternall, and ſo reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces Chaplaine in all dutifull obſeruance, <hi>Nathanael Cannon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17605:4"/>
            <head>A DOVBLE HEART.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. KING. 21.9.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ſhe wrote in the letters, ſaying, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a faſt, and ſet Naboah among the people, and ſet two wicked men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him to beare witneſſe againſt him, ſaying: Thou didſt blaſpheme God and the King, and then ſtone him to death.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Zechiels</hi> Viſion is full of demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 8.8</note>, and in a liuely maner doth preſent vnto vs the courſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther curſe of ſin:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17605:5"/>it ſhewes vs the gradation of it, as if it grew vp by the rule of multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from bad to worſe, from much to more, from one miſchiefe to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vntill the full meaſure of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe and abomination it ſelfe bee made vp. <hi>Goe</hi> (ſaith God vnto the Prophet in that place) <hi>and dig into the wall, and thou ſhalt finde a doore, which doore breake open, and thou ſhalt ſee all manner of abominations: and when thou haſt ſcene thoſe, ſaith God, goe a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then thou ſhalt ſee more, and the further thou goeſt the more abominations thou ſhalt find.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text ſeemeth to haue the like reuelation, for by that time the walls of the Scripture are broken downe, and the doore of it opened, wee ſhall ſee ſuch degrees of ſinne, and ſuch a progreſſion in wickedneſſe, that the truth of that Scripture will appeare vnto vs, which <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes of, as concerning the nature of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is, to draw ſinne vpon ſinne, and iniquitie vpon iniquitie,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17605:5"/>
               <hi>as it were with cart ropes</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.8.</note>.</p>
            <p>This courſe is here taken by a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed woman, for ſo God pronounceth <hi>Iezabel</hi> to bee, who hauing with her husband <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſet their eyes vpon that, which was not their owne and longing after <hi>Naboaths</hi> Vineyard which was neere adioyning vnto their Pallace, they propoſe it vnto him, that they might obtaine it for a price, or els that they might excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge with him for ſome other: but his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is Negatiue: <hi>God forbid</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that I ſhould ſell my fathers inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This refuſal in vnpleaſing to <hi>Ahab,</hi> as if it had beene a great offence in <hi>Naboath</hi> to keepe his owne.</p>
            <p>In this diſcontentment, <hi>Iezabel</hi> takes her time, and of a reſolution to accompliſh her wicked purpoſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſeth <hi>Ahab</hi> after this manner. Art thou a King, ſaith ſhe, and ruleſt Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. As who ſhould ſay, Dares hee denie thee his vineyard.</p>
            <p>Thus are there alwaies wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17605:6"/>to prouoke and worke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly offices, eſpecially where wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed women become counſellors, whoſe mallice is no leſſe then is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs when it maintaind, that there is no head to the head of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 35.</note> nor no malice to the malice of a wicked woman.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of this Text is an inſtance, ſo it is very probable, that <hi>Ahab</hi> would haue giuen this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after a little more grumbling. But <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſcornes ſuch a repulſe, ſhee wil haue his Vineyard and his bloud, and for that purpoſe ſhee arraignes him, condemnes him, and executes him all at once, as appeares in this Text.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing broken downe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the wall to make way vnto it, that ſo we may ſee the occaſion from whence all this proceeds, wee will now adreſſe ourſelues vnto the dore, and looke in thereat, that ſo we may enter into this Scripture, and take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our conſideration ſuch ſeuerals, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17605:6"/>in a courſe of deuiſion, this Text will naturally afford vnto vs, The deuiſion of the Text into three parts.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Naboaths</hi> death.</item>
                  <item>2. The meanes of his death.</item>
                  <item>3. The colouring of his death.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His death is decreed aforehand, <hi>ſtone him to death,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iezabel,</hi> ſhe wil haue it according to the deſperate rule: <hi>Sic volo, ſic iubeo ſtet pro ratione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The meanes of his death, by ſubornation of falſe witneſſe, <hi>Set two wicked men before him,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>and let them accuſe him of blaſphemie against God and the King:</hi> anſwerable to that Popiſh propoſition as Heatheniſh as the former, <hi>inra periuraſecretum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere noli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The pretended color for the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of his death, <hi>Proclaime a faſt,</hi> as if ſhee did commiſerate the mans caſe, and as if he had been iuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and that ſhee for his better preparation to his death would haue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17605:7"/>this faſt proclaimed: partly to haue it conceiued, that ſhee and others were ſorrowfull for his death, but chiefly, that by meanes of ſuch an Aſſembly, and ſo holy any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as faſting was, ſhee would haue it appeare, that ſhee did it to no other end, but onely to bring <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boath</hi> to a feeling of his fault, as if he had deſerued death, and ſhee great commendations for this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and compaſſion towards him in prouiding thus religiouſly (as ſhee would haue it thought) for his pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable departure. Thus the Camelion caſt her colour, and this miſte muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to make many fall into error, ſhe hauing concluded, that it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make this ſhew: <hi>Et ſatis eſt potuiſſe videri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus wee haue taken the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſunder, let vs deſire God to ioyne with vs in the enlargement of the whole. And for aſmuch as the laſt part of this deuiſion, are the firſt words of this Text, I will therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17605:7"/>begin with them, and ſo take them in their courſe as they lie in order.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proclaime a faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simulata ſanctitas eſt duplex iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtin in Pſalm.</hi> 36.</note> a diſſembled holines is double vngodlineſſe.</p>
               <p>It had been wickednes to ſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood, and falſely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne, &amp; cruelly murder the harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and guiltleſſe man, but thus to trick it vp, &amp; color it vnder pretence of pity, doubles the impietie.</p>
               <p>But here is matter of great amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comming forth to meet vs. For firſt of all, it is a trembling buſineſſe, no queſtion, to the wicked them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſhed blood: for it quakes nature, and excludes grace, and cries for vengeance, and proues alwaies ſo diſcouerable, that as wee ſee by daily experience, God ſuffers nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, nor place, nor great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to couer the blood that is ſo barbarouſlie ſhed: would not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17605:8"/>all theſe ſtay the hand, or ſtagger the heart, it is more then a miracle vnto vs,</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is no leſſe to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, that the nature of ſinne ſhould grow to bee ſo deſperate, as to make choiſe of the moſt ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed actions, for their colourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections.</p>
               <p>For example: What action can there be more leading vnto true ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, then our mortification? What leadeth more vnto mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then religiouſly and ſincerely from the bottome of the heart, to hold a religious faſt vnto the Lord.</p>
               <p>Behold, it is here but a vizard to produce a moſt monſtrous and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious acte, Heare, O Heauens, and hearken, O Earth, and maruell, O yee ſonnes of men, at this impudency! O, who ſhould dare to prophane ſuch deuine actions as theſe are, but only thoſe, who are incurable, and ſo vtterly incorrigible, as that they care not, though they act the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17605:8"/>Diuels owne part.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſeth Chriſt
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.48</note>: but hides his treaſon; and ſo <hi>Iezabel,</hi> proclaimes a Faſt, but hides the knife from <hi>Naboaths,</hi> that muſt giue him his death.</p>
               <p>The Panther,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. nat. hiſt. lib.</hi> 8.</note> as (<hi>Pliny</hi> reporteth carrieth with him a ſweete ſent, but an vgly force, therefore he hides his talents, vntil he haue the pray within danger. In like manner <hi>Iezabel</hi> will ſucke the blood of <hi>Naboath,</hi> and yet ſhee hides this venome vnder a faſt proclaime a faſt, ſaith ſhee: from whence we may draw this obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrin. </seg>10</label> Euery ſinne will ſhelter it ſelfe vnder ſome pretence.</head>
               <p>There are no perquiſities of laſting and certaine tenure, but onely thoſe which a crew from vertue: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo quick is our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the point of profit, and our wils ſo abſolute in the doing of euill, that though ſhame run by vs like a lacky, and confuſion prooue the cloſe and full point of our deriuations, yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17605:9"/>will the wicked proceede, and verily perſwade themſelues, there can be no <hi>quare impedit,</hi> either to hinder or cut off them, or their deſignes.</p>
               <p>But it were a neceſſary queſtion to demand of them, why they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe themſelues?
<note place="margin">Ariſtot. Quaedam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur &amp; non ſunt.</note> why they are like <hi>Ariſtotles videnturs,</hi> who affirmes that there are many things ſeemes to be that, which they are not.</p>
               <p>The anſwere will aford it ſelfe, for by their ſhadowes, miſts and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, that they caſt, they doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the people, whereas if they came in the proper reſemblance of their deformed courſes, they would bee more then monſtrous in the eyes of the people; and therefore our Sauiour ſpeakes of theſe pretences, when hee ſhewes, that there are ſome that haue put on ſheepes clothing, but inwardly they are rauening Wolues,
<note place="margin">Sinne aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of it ſelfe.</note> where we may ſee the hatefulneſſe of ſin, that it dares not bee ſeene in his owne likeneſſe, but muſt aſſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſhape for it, the which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17605:9"/>let me now endeuour to proue from the Scriptures, as formerly I propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it in the doctrine, namely, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſinne will ſhelter it ſelfe vnder ſome pretence.</p>
               <p>The Scribes and Phariſies, who were party coluored in all their actions, and clouen-footed in all their treadings, did many foule and fearefull things vnder preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but amongſt all others, how ill did they vſe poore widdowes. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That they deuoured widowes hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ma.</hi> 23.14</note>. How did they deuoure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of long praiers.</p>
               <p>It was a fearefull thing to offer violence vnto them aboue al others: for God commandeth vs to helpe them, to comfort them, and to bee a father to their fatherles: and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhewes, that <hi>this is as the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our religion</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.27.</note>: pure religion and vndefiled before God, is to viſit the fatherles and widowes, ſo that to do them wrong were hatefull: but to oppreſſe them, or to draw blood fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder pretence of ſome prayers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17605:10"/>moſt damnable, for ſo Chriſt affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; therefore, ſaith he, your dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is greater, becauſe of your monſtrous hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> alſo puts on his cloake to his couetouſnes, as appeareth in the Goſpell, <hi>This oyntment,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>would haue been ſold, and the money giuen to the poore,</hi> O what a faire pretence is this, who will or can diſlike that man, which ſhall ſpeak for the poore: but God knew his heart, that it was not vpright. He care for the poore? No ſuch matter: let them ſtarue, ſinke or ſwimme, it was all one to him. This he ſaid, ſaith the Text, not that hee cared for the poore, but that hee was a theefe, and carried the bag; and therefore was loath, that ſuch a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſhould goe from his own mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> alſo ſeems wonderful for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the ſending away of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to <hi>Bethelem,</hi> to ſeeke out the Babe Chriſt, <hi>and when you haue found him, bring me word,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I alſo may come and worſhip him.</hi> Would <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> worſhip Chriſt? No ſuch matter:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17605:10"/>but if he could come at him, he would murther him, for hee is afraid of his crown, as al Tirants are. <hi>Balam</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 23.1</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the glory of God, when hee goes about his magical ſpels, and yet comes the Lord, and calles for altars, <hi>Build me here,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſeuen Alters if ſo be it may pleaſe the Lord to anſwere me.</hi> Hee workes in ſorcery, and yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends great pietie, iuſt after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of in the Epiſtle of
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Titus; They profeſſe that they know God, but in workes they denie him, being abominable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, and vnto euery good worke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus from the Scriptures haue we prooued this doctrine, and further might confirme it from
<note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul,</hi> who vnder the pretence of ſacrifice reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>Agage,</hi> and the reſt of the booty. Further from <hi>Ammon,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 13.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauids</hi> ſon, who pretends ſicknes, to rauiſh his Siſter <hi>Tamar:</hi> from <hi>Ioab,</hi> who vnder pretence of curteſie ſtabs <hi>Amaſa</hi> to the heart
<note n="m" place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 20.9</note>.</p>
               <p>From the Scriptures come vnto
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17605:11"/>our owne times, what is there that we will allow to be ſinne; haue wee not a cloke &amp; a vaile for euery tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. Doth not the couetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhroud himſelfe, vnder pretence of prouiding for his familie
<note n="n" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note>. Doth not the drunkard couch vnder good fellowſhip and loue, doth not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der goe now for manhood: is not ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and excuſing anſwered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with good intents, and what ſinne ſhall there be named, that will not be defended, Alas my brethren, our defenſes and intimations reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, and mentall concluſions, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and euaſions will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vs.</p>
               <p>Amongſt others, if we ſhall looke vpon the example of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6 <hi>Good intents will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</hi>
                  </note> it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to this purpoſe, to put vs from the good intents, when the Ark was in danger of falling, by the ſtumbling of the oxen, hee put forth his hand out of a good intent, out of his loue vnto the Lord; yet in regardd there was a commandement to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Lord was angry with him, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17605:11"/>ſtrikes him dead: the which with all other allegations to this purpoſe, as the Apoſtle meanes in the 3.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> to the Romans, that <hi>we muſt not doe euill, that good may come thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore might raiſe admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but that wee can collect the reaſons, why ſinners wil lodge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnder theſe pretenſes, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie euaſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. They wil doe all their euill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnder good pretences in the imitation of their Maſter the Diuell, whom they ſerue: Satan neuer comes to tempt like a diuell, but to that end that he may blind or deceiue; he will tranſforme himſelfe into an Angell of Light
<note n="q" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note>: and he is ſo cunning in the deluſions that he offereth, <hi>that,</hi> as our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>if it were poſſible, hee would deceiue the very Elect</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</note>.</p>
               <p>This leſſon hath he taught his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, alwaies to pretend ſome good in the wickedeſt actions that can
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17605:12"/>be enterpriſed: and amongſt other maxims and principles of Satan, how foule ſo euer the fact is, yet you muſt not confeſſe it, but either iuſtifie the act vnder ſome good pretence, or elſe ſo extenuate it, as it were, not worthy the reproouing. This ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling our firſt parents kept
<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. <hi>It is one of the Diuels prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples neuer to acknowledge a fault.</hi>
                  </note>: <hi>Adam</hi> ſaith God, <hi>haſt thou eaten of the fruite: The woman,</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>that thou gaueſt me ſhe gaue me, and I did eate.</hi> Marke, it was no ſinne of his, but the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans: yea, he will lay the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon God, as if he had been in the fault for giuing the woman; <hi>The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that thou gaueſt me.</hi> Then to the woman; <hi>Why haſt thou done this: The Serpent,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>beguiled me, and I did eate.</hi> Thus they poſte their ſinnes one from another. This tricke Satan hath taught all his: for the thiefe in his deedes of darkeneſſe vſeth the night, that none may ſee him: but if he be brought to light. Why then, what would you haue me doe? I am in wants, and I was aſhamed to beg, and I could not worke; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17605:12"/>I did this for neceſſities ſake.</p>
               <p>The Fornicator or Adulterer being made manifeſt, doth hee take it to heart, in that he broke the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement? No verily: but when his finne is vrged, his excuſe is ready; Why, it is but a tricke of youth, and I am not the firſt; and if all our ſinnes were written in our foreheads, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might bee aſhamed to ſhew their faces, as well as I; and therefore ſaith he, <hi>Let him that hath done no ſinne caſt the firſt ſtone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Curſer and common blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, that rips vp the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Chriſt, and ſweares, <hi>ex tempore,</hi> at euerie word is he to blame, when his ſinne is cald in queſtion, and he told, <hi>that the plague of God is vpon that houſe, where aſwearer is, and lieth betweene the wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot and the wall</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.4.</note>. Doth this either moue him, or reforme him, no not at all but he will defend it: why did you prouoke me, then (ſaith he) it is your ſinne to vrge me (ſaith he) and not mine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17605:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ieſabel</hi> and her diſciples will haue pretences, to giue ſome kind of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as it were, to the common people, eſpecially, if it concerne a publike action, for ſo <hi>Iezabel</hi> carrieth this. <hi>Naboath</hi> is ſet in the midſt of the people, and a faſt is proclaimed, and euery thing carried in that piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner, as if none had been more mooued with compaſſion then <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> yet becauſe he was a blaſphemer, he muſt needs die, but in the manner of his death, ſhe would ſhew all the fauour that could be,
<note place="margin">A Similitude</note> like vnto ſome theeues, who when they haue ſtript a man out of all he hath, would faine be accounted mercifull theeues, in that they do not murder thoſe whom they haue robbed, or in that they do not bind them ſo cruelly, as ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done. Thus that bloodie Emperor wold be accounted pitiful,
<note place="margin">Nero.</note> in that he let his ſchool-maſter die an eaſie death, wheras it was monſtrous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17605:13"/>crueltie in him to do him to death at al, eſpecially vpon no better ground, but becauſe he whipt him when hee was his Scholler. But let vs gather towards the harueſt of our doctrine, and that is ſuch profitable vſes, as may bee deriued from this point, which ſhewes vs, that euery ſin will ſhelter it ſelfe vnder ſome pretence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. This ſhewes what a fearefull ſinne couetouſneſſe is, the which this action of <hi>Iezabels</hi> will demonſtrate vnto vs, for her walke was large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, one would haue thought ſhe had but a whole Kingdome, and yet that was not compaſſe enough: but ſhe lackt a herb-Garden, for ſo the Text ſaith.
<note place="margin">Couetouſnes like the dropſie.</note> This ſinne hath a great dropſie belly; and though it be neuer ſo full already, yet it muſt haue more, and nothing will ſatiſfie it. A pitiful caſe, that a whole kingdome ſhould not afford a King a Herbe-garden, but hee muſt take it from another
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17605:14"/>man. This is, as I ſaid before a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſinne: for this <hi>Iudas,</hi> will betray Chriſt
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.</note>: this is the roote of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<note n="w" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note>: for this, many a man ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſoule. But <hi>what ſhall it profit a man,</hi> becauſe they talke of profit, <hi>to get the whole world, and loſe his ſoule</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.36.</note>. Take heede of this ſin, if you would haue gaine, get godlineſſe, for that is great gaine, if a man be contented with that he hath; which if <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezabel</hi> had been, they had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of this great offence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whenſoeuer we are tempted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſinne and money or gifts offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs. Let vs ſay, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith vnto <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy money pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with thee,</hi> and this is our firſt vſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This doctrine ſerues to make vs acquainted with a certaine gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whom Chriſt calles hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, or generation of Vipers
<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ma.</hi> 23.33</note>. You ſhall know them by my text: for they will ſpeake one thing, but act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; they will proclaime a faſt, but execute murder; they ſay, and do
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17605:14"/>not, ſaith Chriſt:
<note place="margin">An Hipocrite compared vnto a Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</note> theſe are ſpirituall iuglers, who can ſhew trickes, but it is all to deceiue the people. So in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the hypocrite with all his paſſe and repaſſe, doth but deceiue his owne ſoule: but bee not deceiued, faith the Apoſtle, God is not
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.</note> moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; we may blind the world, and we may for a time get our own wills, and ſerue our owne turnes, but this will turne to our deſtruction at laſt. Let vs therefore deteſt hypocriſie, becauſe God doth deteſt the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite: <hi>He that ſpeakes the truth from the heart, ſhall enter into the Tabernacle</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 15.</note>. Then they that diſſemble, and wroke wickedneſſe vnder faire pretences ſhall not: Away then with our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable proteſtations and forged actions, we many times ſpeake faire vnto the face, when we wiſh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and confuſion of them, whom we thus ſalute. If this be not a fearefull ſin, what will we account to be ſinne. This is ſo common, that it ſtumbles many a man now adaies in his choiſe of friends: for the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17605:15"/>men, the Lord helpe the while, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.1.</note> are gone and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the face of the earth; and therefore it is not amiſſe for men wel to conſider, whom they truſt, with whom they conuerſe. Yea it is not much digreſsiue from the text, to bid them take head after whom they eat or drinke, for diets now adaies are not altogether ſo wholeſome, as they haue been heretofore, neither were hypocrites ſo dangerous, for they were wont to hurt but their owne ſoules, and now their hypocriſie in many things tends to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others: let as many then as loue the Lord hate this ſinne: For God endures not a heart, and a heart: but the true Iſraelites are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the men in whom are found no guile, are onely the ingredients into his kingdome.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This point teacheth vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an circumſpection euen in diuine matters: there are thoſe that profeſſe God, and yet ſerue the diuell, there are thoſe that come in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17605:15"/>thing, but inwardly are rauening
<note place="margin">An hypocrite like a Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</note> but inwardly are rauening Wolues, and theſe men are ſo expert, and with the Camelion, ſeeme of any colour, that if it were poſsible, they would deceiue the very elect
<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24</note>. <hi>Try the ſpirits therefore,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn, and beleeue not euery ſpirit, but ſee firſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God or not</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.1.</note>. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhews them vnto vs, as it were out of a table
<note n="f" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note>: when he ſaith, that they haue onely a forme of godlines, or a ſhew therof, and theſe are hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creepers, for ſo the Apoſtle accounts them, when he ſaith, that they creepe into houſes, and leade captiue ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple women. Of theſe alſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes in the 1. of Timothie
<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2</note>, that teach doctrines of diuels, and ſpeake lies, ſaith he, through hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: let vs therefore ſhut our eyes from theſe Baſiliſks, and our eares from theſe Syrens, leſt we be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It ſerues for an excellent rule vnto all our actions, namely, that we proportion them according to Gods word, which is not colourable, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17605:16"/>warantable, plaine, and without eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if we proceede after this maner, then we may ſay as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> doth
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 5.39.</note>: <hi>If it bee of God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it ſhall ſtand, otherwiſe it will fall to the ground.</hi> Let euery man remember this, that meanes to haue his actions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It ſerues for an admonition vnto great perſons, and as it is ſaid of old, <hi>Remember Lots wife</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.26</note>: ſo ſay I, Remember <hi>Iezabel:</hi> no queſtion ſhe did not thinke, that God would haue reuenged this hypocriſie ſo deepely. And againe, there is no doubt but ſhee did apprehend her owne great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as who ſhould ſay, if it ſhould be knowne, yet who dares ſpeake of it, or if they ſpeak, yet what can they doe. Here we may ſee how they ſcape for all their greatnes. God firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couers it, to ſhew, that though they haue blinded the world, yet they cannot blind him. Secondly, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengeth it ſoundly, ten for one, not one of <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe ſhall ſcape, and for the woman, author and actor of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17605:16"/>
                  <hi>Naboaths</hi> death, ſhe made the dogges ſuch a feaſt, that they neuer licked ſuch blood before
<note n="k" place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 9.36.</note>, &amp; this is al the account that God maketh of the greateſt, when they forſake him. O conſider this you tall and loftie Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, I ſay, remember that there is a God.</p>
               <p>Thus haue we helpt to pull of this vizard of ſinne, which <hi>Iezabel</hi> hath here put vpon a ſhamefull murder, thinking it ſufficient to haue a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and to pretend ſomething, that may be colourable, although the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing action bee neuer ſo abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, anſwerable to that diueliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>Machiauel,</hi> who ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Machiauel cap.</hi> 18. <hi>De principe.</hi>
                  </note> that it is enough for a great man to ſeeme deuout, and to make ſhew of that, which he is not, a diueliſh document and a propoſition of more practiſe, then pietie throughout al the world: let vs therefore proceede with that which followeth in this text.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17605:17"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> The meanes of <hi>Naboaths</hi> death: <q>
                     <hi>Set two wicked men before him, and let them accuſe him.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If the eye be ſingle, ſaith Chriſt, the whole body will bee ſingle
<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22.</note>: which ſhewes, that the ſight is the chiefe among the ſenſes, as the heart is among the members, the which being well affected, a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, yea, a very confluence of goodnes enſueth to the whole body. But here <hi>Iezabel</hi> hath caſt her eie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an vnlawfull obiect, and a ſecret conueyance is made by a couetous heart to entitle her vnto another mans vineyard. The Logicians ſay truly, that <hi>(color eſt obiectum viſus)</hi> but this doth not ſatiſfie <hi>Iezabel:</hi> for to ſee this vineyard, but her eye hath taught her heart to couet, her heart hath imploid her head for deuiſe, and her head hath thought vpon the vſe of a tongue, a falſe, ſlanderous and curſed tongue which ſhall accuſe this innocent man: truly hath Saint
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17605:17"/>
                  <hi>Iames</hi> ſpoken of an euill ſpeaking tongue, when hee ſaith, that it is a world of wickednes, and ful of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poiſom
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 3.8</note>: deadly indeed, for the falſe tongue is here <hi>Naboaths</hi> death.</p>
               <p>This ſin of ſlaunder, and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, is the diuels owne ſinne: for he is called the accuſer of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, hee that accuſeth day and night
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.10.</note>. So then by this account the falſe accuſer or ſlanderer is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diuell.</p>
               <p>This ſinne comprehends many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> notes very witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Eraſmus com. de lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua.</note> 
                  <hi>Damihi mendacem &amp; ego oſtendam tibi furem:</hi> If thou wilt ſhew me a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, ſaith he, I will ſhew thee a thiefe; and no doubt but theſe will beget manyothers. Now as it draws on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſins, ſo it exceeds many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins,
<note place="margin">Luther. loc. com. ling.</note> 
                  <hi>ter homicida calumniator &amp; v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ictu tres occidit:</hi> the ſlanderer, or falſe accuſer, ſaith hee, kills three at one blow the partie to whom, the partie of whom, and himſelfe. The Theefe ſendes but one to the diuell, for hee hurts but his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17605:18"/>his owne ſoule; the adulterer ſends two to the diuell, vnleſſe he repent, both their ſoules are in danger: but the falſe accuſer ſends three to the diuell, this is the ſinne that <hi>Ieſabel</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues vpon for the diſpatch of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boath,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then it will be time for vs to gather towards ſome point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for our preſent inſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naboath</hi> is innocent, and yet muſt die; not ſecretly, but by a publique ſentence of Law, by meanes of eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence giuen againſt him, which char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him, but falſely, for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming God and the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> From whence wee learne, that when there is no iuſt cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the innocent, then doe the wicked deuiſe ſome matter againſt them.</p>
               <p>It is no eaſie matter to bring the godly inqueſtion, if truth might take place: for they keepe a narrow watch ouer their waies, carefull what they ſpeake, of whom, to whom, as careful what they doe, and for the moſt part
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17605:18"/>aske counſell of God, as concerning their actions; and this they doe not <hi>formidme poenae,</hi> but <hi>virtutis amore,</hi> not for feare of puniſhment, which were ſeruile, but for the loue they beare vnto God which is filiall: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Chriſtian circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet they are many times in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaths</hi> caſe, that is, falſely accuſed, for want of matter, it ſhall be made and deuiſed, as <hi>Iezabel</hi> here directs, <hi>ſet two wicked men before him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> is in this caſe,
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.18</note> for they that hated him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iewes did long lie in waite to haue ſome matter againſt him, but the Lord did ſo keepe him, as that they could not iuſtly accuſe him: What then, will they let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? No verily, they will take a courſe with him. Come, ſay they, let vs deuiſe ſome matter againſt <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi> let vs ſmite him with our tongues: this is the courſe that they will take with him; they will firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe ſome matter, then they wil ſmite him with the tongue, where we may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17605:19"/>note what a wicked tongue is, euen a ſharp raſor, or a two edged ſword, to cut aſſunder the very life or good name of an innocent.</p>
               <p>The like courſe is taken with Chriſt, the Scribes and Phariſees re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to perſecute and crucifie Chriſt, <hi>Iudas</hi> betraies him, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and officers carrie him, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple crie againſt him, <hi>Crucifie him, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him, his blood be vpon vs and our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie. Pilate</hi> ſits vpon him, and yet for all this, he is conſtrained to ſay, though he loued not Chriſt: <hi>I finde</hi> ſaith <hi>Pilate, no euill in him, what hath he done, that you would haue him condemned.</hi> Yet this doth not ſtay their fury: but at length two falſe accuſers are ſet before him, and two wicked ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers ſtand vp againſt him: but <hi>till</hi> then, <hi>Pilate</hi> acquitteth him, ſaying, <hi>I finde no fault in this man, touching thoſe things that you accuſe him.</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk</hi> 23.14</note>
               </p>
               <p>Poore innocent <hi>Ioſeph</hi> grones vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the like burden, for he is accuſed euen for righteouſneſſe ſake, and his incontinent Miſtriſſe miſſing of her
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17605:19"/>purpoſe, in that hee will not conſent to abuſe his Maſters bed, ſhee then deuiſeth againſt him, and accuſeth him, that he attempted her chaſtitie, and would haue lien with her
<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.14</note>: for which he ſuffers impriſonment, vntil the Lord lookt vpon him, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to a double honour, making him head and ruler ouer all Egypt.</p>
               <p>The like tricke hath that ſaucy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Ziba,</hi> againſt his Maſter <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſeth</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">2. <hi>Sa.</hi> 16.3.</note>, poſſeſſing <hi>Dauid</hi> with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt him that he neuer thought as if <hi>Mephiboſeth</hi> ſhould haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to aſpire the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the coiners and plotters of miſchiefe, theſe men are neuer out of matter, for they are turned diuels, and can fit any man that ſhall offend them, they haue their articles and bils of inditement as readily framed as can bee, and for their witneſſes, they haue ſure cardes, ſuch as make haſte to kiſſe the booke, leſt they ſhould forget ſome of that forged vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie, which muſt bee broched for the diſpatch of the innocent.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17605:20"/>
               <p> Thus the firſt part of ſlander is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<note place="margin">Slander or falſe accuſing hath diuers acceptions.</note> or rather deuiſed: for indeed firſt of all, it is taken vp, or entertained in the minde, where it is firſt thought vpon or forged, as was this againſt <hi>Naboath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the tongues of others muſt divulge and publiſh it, as theſe two wicked men that are his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers here doe, and ſo like a leproſie it runnes vp and downe, by meanes whereof, a freſh ſpring ariſeth, and with a new edition, it comes foorth in print as it were, and by that time a great many ſlanderers are begotten; who relate it as confidently, as if it were true indeede. Thus this ſlander that at the firſt was inuented, or ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by groſſe, is afterwards ſold by retaile, and they walke vp and downe with it, as it were, ſo many pedlers, and wherſoeuer they come, they open the packe, and ſhew what wares the diuel hath furniſhed them withall.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a ſlander is committed, by giuing eare vnto a falſe report, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17605:20"/>though thou doe not deuiſe it, as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel</hi> doth, nor publiſh it, as the two falſe witneſſes heere doe, yet if thou receiue it, and approoue of it, if thou giue eare vnto it and beleeue it, thou art a ſlaunderer, which is intimated vnto vs, when it is made a marke of Gods childe in thee
<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 15.</note>: not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an euill report againſt his neighbour. This reacheth farre, and faſteneth vpon many in theſe our daies, and with the Athenians
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.21</note>: we ſtill aske newes, and if any thing come out againſt any man, eſpecially againſt him or them, that we doe not loue, then we firſt beleeue it, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, ſet vpon it as furiouſly, as if wee were very Fenſers, and would play ſuch a prize, that euery body ſhould thinke wee were not our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Thus we play at Tennis, with the good names of other men, but vpon great diſaduantage: for in this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis court, we haue extraordinary ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards. We hazard our iudgements, in receiuing raſh reports. Secondly,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17605:21"/>wee hazard our diſcretion in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them; and thirdly, wee hazard our religion in publiſhing them, and railing vpon them, whom we thus ſet vpon: for
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26</note> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, if a man ſeeme to bee religious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraines not his tongue, that mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is all in vaine: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, yet this vnruly member will flie about, and dart at Gods dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt children, very few of them ſhall be free from the venome of it.</p>
               <p>In this courſe the wicked will bee agents,
<note place="margin">The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous may be reuenged on them that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them falſely.</note> and the moſt righteous muſt be true patients, and yet the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous know, how to be reuenged when they will, and that is by following the counſell of God, namely, when they curſe, the godly muſt bleſſe, and when their enemies and accuſers are hungrie, let the godly feede them, if thirſty, let them giue them drinke, and in ſo doing, they ſhall heape coales of fire on their heads
<note n="w" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.20</note>: let them commit and commend their cauſes vnto the Lord, for vengeance is his, and he will repay it
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 21.19</note>: and let
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17605:21"/>this ſuffice for the doctrine, which was deriued from the ſecond part of this deuiſion, which was the meanes vſed to bring <hi>Naboath</hi> to his death, namely, falſe witnes: now let vs ſee what applications will iſſue from hence vnto vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vſes.</head>
               <p>Our firſt ingredience will afford vs a Caution, take heede of this little me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, it may hurt many waies, but it ſtabs to the very hart, when it is vſed in this kind to ſlander, or accuſe the innocent: take heede thou that deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt: take heed thou that reporteſt, and take heede thou that beleeueſt any thing againſt the innocent, there are many reaſons why thou ſhouldeſt hearken to this caution.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe God followes that man with a ſword to deſtroy him, and to cut him off, which he threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens in the <hi>Pſa.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>He that priuily ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth his neighbour, him will I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17605:22"/>
               <p> Secondly, euery one that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne, is of the diuell
<note n="z" place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note>: but this is the diuels owne ſinne. Now if thou wouldeſt not be accounted a diuell, be not guilty of this ſinne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if thou be ſpirituall, thou wilt reſtore a man with the ſpirit of meekenes that is falne, as the Apoſtle
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</note> exhorteth: knowing that we our ſelues alſo may fall. But one the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, we rather delight in theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, then labor to couer them: but if it were a curſed thing in <hi>Cham</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 9.14</note> to diſcouer his fathers nakednes, it muſt needes bee a wretched thing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large, amplifie, and make an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our brethrens infirmities, but a curſed thing to deuiſe matter, that ſhall hurt their innocent ſoules; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the rule of charitie this ſin would be forborne, becauſe charitie neuer thinketh, much leſſe doth euill to the brethren.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a reaſon for this caueat might be drawne from the rule of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, which bids vs doe vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, euen as we our ſelues would be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17605:22"/>delt withall: but wee would grieue and vexe to heare, that men ſhould accuſe and raile vpon vs, wee would be loath to haue our life or credit lie vpon the accuſation of a falſe tong: then proportion things vnto others,
<note place="margin">Doe as thou wouldeſt be done by.</note> as thou wouldeſt receiue <hi>fac alijs fieri quod cupis ipſe tibi,</hi> if thou wouldeſt that men ſhouldſt not make the worſt conſtruction of thee: bee not thou like vnto a cupping glaſſe,
<note place="margin">A Slaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer like a cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping glaſſe, which onely drawes ill matter.</note> which only drawes that humor that is euil and corrupt; ſo doth the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer onely apply his tongue to falſe accuſation and euill ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>The ſecond vſe is to ſhew, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and ſound condition of an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life; if any man will doe them hurt, he muſt doe it by lies and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, for the righteous are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and the bleſſing of God is ſo vpon them, that they do not lie open to dangers and imputations as other men doe, and yet no men ſo often in queſtion, and ſo ſubiect to falſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions as they, but for the moſt part it is deuiſed and enlarged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17605:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17605:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17605:24"/>them: it ſhewes that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God is as a ſhield to couer them, and yet for all this, Satan hath fiery darts, and maleuolent courſes againſt them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This will teach vs to charge a watch ouer all our members, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially our tongues: <hi>O Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, ſet a watch before the doore of my lippes, that I offend not with my tongue</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 141.1</note>. May a man bee a murderer with his tongue, O then watch that member, forbeare to heare euill, forbeare to ſpeake euill: <hi>ſi deeſt auditor, deeſt &amp; de tractor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom.</note> if the hearer would forbeare, the ſlaunderer would ceaſe: for the ſinne of ſlaunder gets a kind of nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from a willing hearer, and yet both are ſo dangerous, that as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> obſerueth,
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                  <hi>dum aurem inficit, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam interficit:</hi> ſo bad a ſeaſon muſt needs haue a curſed harueſt: let vs therfore bridle our affections, and let grace ouercome nature in this euill, and this ſhall ſuffice to ſhew the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diſpoſition of the wicked, who doe ſo hate the godly, and are ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17605:24"/>bent in their owne purpoſes, that though they haue no iuſt cauſe to accuſe the righteous of, yet they will inuent, and with <hi>Iezabel,</hi> ſet wicked men before them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and condemne the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This ſerues to pacifie and to appeaſe the working, that theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations and accuſations would worke in vs, if God did not ſtay vs: ſurely theſe ſlanders and falſe reports and dangerous attempts againſt vs, may with other afflictions bee fitly compared vnto phiſick,
<note place="margin">Affliction like phiſick.</note> the which we take from the phiſition to make vs well, and ſo with the bleſſing of God it doth, yet at the firſt it makes vs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſicke, vntill ſuch time as it hath purged the ſtomack, and clenſed it. ſo verily, our afflictions make vs ſick to the death, and bring vs very low at the firſt, vntill it hath clenſed our hearts of all vindictiue humors, of all earthly humours of all ſuperfluous matter, then we ſhall finde health euen ſauing health, and bee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17605:25"/>ſo reſtored, that wee will not feare thoſe, that can but kill the body, but onely <hi>feare him, that can kill body and ſoule, and caſt them both into ouerlaſting hell fire</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note>. And herewithall let vs conclude this point.</p>
               <p>Now in the laſt place we ſhall be brought to behold the wofull trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of poore <hi>Naboath, Stone him to death,</hi> ſaith ſhe, that is the <hi>Terminus ad ad quem,</hi> of all this buſineſſe hee muſt die, and thereby he ſhall know, what it is to croſſe ſuch a woman as <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> was of her will.</p>
               <p>Here ſinne begins to troope and march forward one after another ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fairely, and as if they had learned a helliſh diſcipline, they keepe ranke in ſuch an orderly manner, that you may tell them, and eaſily diſcerne how one hath begotten another, let vs therefore calculate how this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, and to what paſſe it is now come.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> as a mother ſin, conceiued, and in this conception or breeding fell to long, and that ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17605:25"/>that the very delay of obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, brought foorth hatred in ſo deadly a manner, that nothing but the death of the obſtacle <hi>Naboath</hi> can ſerue the turne, this curſed daughter, I meane hatred, the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of couetouſneſſe hath ſat in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and hath concluded, that if <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boath</hi> were done to death, then all were hers, but this will require help, the helpe of ſuch bloodſuccours, as muſt draw from <hi>Naboath</hi> both life and breath, and blood, and vineyard and all.</p>
               <p>Thus one ſinne waites vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one begets another,
<note place="margin">Vno dato ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdo mille ſequuntur.</note> and you may tel them how they proceed in a helliſh order.</p>
               <p>Firſt, here is hypocriſie: <hi>Proclaime a faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Slander: <hi>let two accuſe him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Murder: <hi>Stone him to death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This progreſſe of ſinne will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this doctrine very naturally from this latter part.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> That the vngodly proceede by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17605:26"/>degrees from one ſinne to another. As <hi>Romulus</hi> made ſlaughter of his brother <hi>Rhemus,</hi> to that end, that hee might ſettle the Kingdome in his owne perſon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de cinttat. Dei lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: ſo verily, this woman butcher, or butcherly woman wil not giue ouer, vntil ſhe bath her ſelfe in blood, euen in the blood of her adioyning neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, that ſhe may ſettle his vineyard into her owne poſſeſsion: how ſhee hath begun we haue heard, like a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſhew. Proclaime a Faſt: as if a father would haue at the death of a child a ſolemne funerall, together with a ſermon of the ſame nature, to preach mortality vnto the liuing: thus with a ſhew of natural affection ſhee appeareth in the 1. ſcane, in the 2. ſhe hath her deponents, who with graue aſpect before the iudges of the land, call God to witnes, by vertue of an oath that <hi>Naboath</hi> was a blaſphemer, and in the 3. ſhe ſtrikes him downe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a deadly blow, <hi>Stone him to death:</hi> this is the perambulation of the wicked, they proceed from worſe to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17605:26"/>worſe, from one ſinne to another.</p>
               <p>This
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.18</note> 
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> noteth in the fifth Chapter of his Propheſie, when hee ſaith, that the vngodly doe draw ſinnes together, as it were with cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropes: let vs note the phraſe the Prophet vſeth, they draw ſinnes, it is a phraſe to expreſſe the greateſt ſtrength of any creature, the horſe in his greateſt ſtrength and force is ſaid to draw, and it intimateth in mankind the putting on of forces, as if we ſhould ſay, they vſe their wits, words, workes, and all their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to this purpoſe, and they pull them as it were with cart-ropes, where the Prophet giueth to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that beſides their owne ſtrength, they vſe all other meanes and adiunctes heereunto, that ſo the full meaſure of ſin may bee made vp.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſhewes the ſame gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, euery man is tempted,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 1.14</note> ſaith he, when hee is drawne away by his owne concupiſcence. Then 2. when this luſt hath conceiued, it bringeth foorth ſinne: And then 3. this ſinne
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17605:27"/>muſt haue a time to worke, and at length to finiſh. And then fourthly when that is finiſhed, it bringeth foorth death.</p>
               <p>This wee ſee both in the falles of them, who were giuen ouer to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and alſo in the failings of thoſe, whom God did raiſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caine</hi> firſt of all did ſecretly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at his brother <hi>Abel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Examples of both ſorts.</note> but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hee bore deadly hatred vnto him. Thirdly, he murdered him with the jaw bone of an Aſſe. Fourthly, being conuicted as it were before God, in a queſtion that might haue led him to repentance, he anſweth as wickedly as before he had done,
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Am I my brothers keeper.</hi> The like we find in <hi>Indas</hi> his firſt ſinne noted vnto vs, was couetouſneſſe, hee grumbles at the poore womans liberalitie, when ſhe powred that pretious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent vpon Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.5.6.</note> this would haue bin ſold, and giuen to the poore: his meaning was for his own priuat purſe for the text ſaith, <hi>He carried the bagge:</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17605:27"/>
               <p> After this not hauing repented, he falls into a higher degree of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, for now for thirty peeces he will ſell and betray his owne Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note>. After that, he proceeds vnto the worſt of all, and that was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of the mercies of God.
<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
                  <hi>O no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſub quo nemini deſperandum eſt,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this ſtrong anchor of ſaluation to all beleeuers
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19.</note>: yet hee proceedeth to his owne execution, he went and hanged himſelfe: thus wickednes doth multiplie and hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vpon the heads of them, who haue not called vpon God for true repentance.</p>
               <p>This wee may further ſee in thoſe, whom God hath forgiuen and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</p>
               <p>Firſt, our firſt parents, how did they multiply euen at the firſt: <hi>Euah</hi> lookes vpon the fruite. Secondly, ſhe holds a conference with Satan. Thirdly, ſhe taſts of it though it were forbidden. Fourthly, ſhee giues her husband, to make him as guilty as her felfe. Fiftly, ſhee excuſeth her
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17605:28"/>fact, and extenuateth it, when God queſtions her
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.</note>.</p>
               <p>The like wee finde in <hi>Dauid,</hi> that man of God, who
<note n="l" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.</note> firſt hauing ſeene the nakedneſſe of <hi>Bethſheba,</hi> ſends for her, then hee committeth folly with her, then vpon her proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with child ſends for <hi>Vriah</hi> her husband, and at his comming, vſeth all meanes to make him lie with his wife, that ſo he might haue ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his wickedneſſe, and to that ende laboureth to make him drunke: but when this would not take place, then he proceedes to blood; and for this purpoſe, writes vnto <hi>Ioah</hi> the Captaine of the Hoaſt, that he might be placed in the forefront of the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, that ſo he might be ſmitten and die, the which was effected, and ſo innocent <hi>Vriah</hi> murdered.</p>
               <p>The like gradation we find in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who at the firſt out of a fainting feare is afraid to confeſſe his Maſter, but very peremptorily denieth, that euer he knew him, afterwards being thereunto preſſed, he growes deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17605:28"/>offended, and at laſt hee ſweares and curſeth, he neuer knew the man, all which will ſhew vs, how farre wee ſhall goe in a courſe of wickedneſſe, if God doe not ſtay vs.</p>
               <p>Sinne will begin to poſſeſſe that man, that doth not reſiſt it, and break it of in time, for it enters in three waies, as one of the learned obſerues.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Blandiendo,</hi> firſt,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Degrees in a courſe of ſin.</hi>
                  </note> it ſmiles vpon vs like the ſtrumpet, Prou. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Delectando,</hi> Secondly, it takes away our hearts, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> would ſteale away the hearts of the people: 2. Samuel.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Regnando,</hi> Thirdly, it takes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion like the ſtrong man
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 11.</note>: then whoſe are we vntill a ſtronger come, and caſt him out: thus the wicked they decline ſinne <hi>per omnes caſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innominatino per ſuperbiam, in geniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoper luxuriam, in datiuo per Symoniam, in accuſatiuo per detractationem, in voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to per adulationem, in ablatiuoper rapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> and yet for all theſe, <hi>Iezabel</hi> and her crew are certainely perſwaded, that they can ſinne, and not be ſeene.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17605:29"/> 1. <note place="margin">Reaſons for the progreſſe of ſinne.</note> Sinne groweth in the heart, as the child doth in the wombe: for as the infant hath his increaſings, euen by degrees, vntill he come to ſee the light, and bee borne into the world, according as <hi>Iob</hi> hath it:
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 10.10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt powred me out as milke, and turned me into curds like cheeſe, thou haſt clothed mee with skinne and fleſh, thou haſt ioyned mee together with bones and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes.</hi> So is it with the vngodly man, his beginnings were but euill ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, which hee neuer reſiſted, then afterwards out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his heart his mouth ſpake, either falſely, furiouſly, or fainedly, which he neuer repented, and then at length he becomes all theſe, and acts any part of wickedneſſe whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> The iudgements of God are vpon ſuch men, as neuer made conſcience of leſſer ſinnes, by meanes whereof they are at length giuen ouer to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe, and become paſt fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which the Apoſtle notes
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28</note>, that as they haue not regarded to know God, ſo the Lord hath giuen
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17605:29"/>them vp to their owne hearts luſts to worke all maner of wickedneſſe: and this comes firſt of all by the little or no account that we make of ſinne,
<note place="margin">Bernard. Tract. de de gradibus hum.</note> at firſt: this, as that father noteth vpon the point of excuſing or extenuating ſinne, when ſinne is found out, and the queſtion is, who hath, done it? the ſinner anſwereth, <hi>Nonfaeci,</hi> if that will not ſerue the turne but that it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then tis turned, <hi>Si faeci non male faeci,</hi> if the euill be proued, then it is tranſlated, <hi>ſi male faeci, non multum male,</hi> if the qualitie and quantitie be proued, then it hath a fourth eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>ſi multum male, non male intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne:</hi> if good or euill intents bee by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie confuted, then our laſt refuge is, <hi>aliena tamenfaeci perſwaſione,</hi> and thus we ſpin out iniquitie and giue it ſucke from ſuch a breſt of maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and excuſe, as if it were very lawfull to doe euill.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore deſcend vnto the life of this doctrine &amp; that is to ſhew our vſes and applications.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:17605:30"/>
               <head>Vſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. All theſe proofes, reaſons, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and illuſtrations doe eccho foorth vnto vs this firſt vſe, <hi>Principijs obſta:</hi> looke to the beginning of euil, kill ſinne in the neaſt, before it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorth, for it hath a curſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, thou muſt ſet a watch ouer thy mouth, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,
<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 39.</note> thou muſt make a couenant with thine eies
<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note>: thou muſt examine thine hart
<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 4.</note>: if it be a proud hart at the firſt, it wil after ſpawne foorth into a falſe heart, if become a falſe heart, it will not bee long, before it be a cruell heart: if it grow to be a cruel heart, a little time will make it a hard heart, if it be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, then ſurely the next degree muſt needs be a reprobate ſenſe, the very iudgement, that God ſuffers the moſt vngodly to fall into: O then ſtay the beginnings of wickedneſſe, and follow the deuine counſell of thy Chriſt, who wiſheth thee to look vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy members, and if thine eie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17605:30"/>thee, to pluck it out, if thy hand offend thee, to cut it off, that is, cut or take away that ſinne, that groweth by meanes of thine eie or thy hand, and doe it in time, leaſt with the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie it run further and further.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the many diſeaſes, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies that happen vnto mans body, there is one that they call by the name of <hi>Gangren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gren.</note> which doth affect altogether the ioynts, and the preſent remedy thereof is immediatly to cut off that firſt ioint, which is firſt affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or elſe it preſently taketh ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo from that vnto a third, vnleſſe it be thus ordered by deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this is the nature of ſinne, which vnleſſe it bee cut off in the motion, proceedeth vnto the action, from the action vnto delectation,
<note place="margin">Ariſtot. log. Habitus est difficulter mobilis a ſubiecto.</note> from delectation vnto aſſuefaction or cuſtome, from that vnto a habite neuer to bee remooued, a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous leproſie, both for infection and diſperſion, vnleſſe there be a timely preuention.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17605:31"/>
               <p> Let this bee conſidered in all our temptations vnto ſinne,
<note place="margin">Thetheefe.</note> if it be vnto ſtealth, we begin with a pin, then a point, then a ſhilling, then a pound, at length any thing: O let the young thiefe take heede of an olde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnleſſe hee repent and leaue that ſinne.</p>
               <p>It may bee they haue eſcaped ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times and that emboldens them, but hee that leades them will neuer leaue them, vntill they are left vnto the law both of God and man, vnles they ſtay theſe beginnings by true touch of conſcience.</p>
               <p>The adulterer doth not preſently fall vpon the bed to commit wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">The adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.</note> but firſt his eye ſends a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to his heart, his heart giues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto the action, and then the time and place, purpoſe is concluded, whereas if the eye went ſingle the whole body would haue bene ſingle and that firſt reſtraint, would cut off the curſed conſequents that alwaies do proceede from that ſinne.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17605:31"/>
               <p> The lyar,
<note place="margin">The lier. Mendacium, pernicioſum, officioſum, ioco ſum.</note> who kills his owne ſoule and vents falſhoods of al ſorts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to deſtroy a Brother, as theſe falſe witneſſes did againſt <hi>Naboath,</hi> ſometimes out of their pretended charitie to ſaue anger, or preuent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, ſometimes out of the olde wiues Calender, tell ſtrange and merrie lyes, fables of great antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and no leſſe iniquitie, all theſe lies had their beginning, which ſhould haue beene ſuppreſſed at the firſt, but for want thereof maketh the ingredient ſo perfect, that a man cannot beleeue one word, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of his mouth, and if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that ſuch a man ſpeake truth which is but ſildome, yet it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and it is iuſt vpon a lyer ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king trueth, but ſildome neuer to be beleeued. O then ſeaſon thy mouth at firſt with trueth, for thy God is a God of trueth, and in that thou haſt not preuented this ſinne in time,
<note place="margin">Mendaci ne credas, ne iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiquidem.</note> thou haſt loſt thy birth-right for the lyars cannot call God their Father, for they haue a father by themſelues,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17605:32"/>euen the diuell, who is the father of lies
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44.</note>; ſtay therefore theſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, leſt the latter end proue feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto thee: for thou canſt not ſhake of theſe things when thou wilt; and therefore doe it when thou mayeſt:
<note place="margin">Conſuetudo eſt altera na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura.</note> take heede of a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome in euill, for a Blackemoore ſhall ſooner change his hue, or a Leopard his ſpots, then they ſhall euer doe good, that haue been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed vnto euill.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23</note>
               </p>
               <p>So then let vs conclude this vſe, cure the diſeaſe in time, before it grow incurable, whether it be pride, enuie, ſlander, diſobedience, deceit, oppreſſion, reuenge, prophaneneſſe, adulteries, falſhoods, murmurings, treacherous practiſes, or the like: clenſe thy heart in time, leſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come incorrigible and inconuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which muſt needes be damnable in the latter end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>This ſerues to diſplay the diuels
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17605:32"/>hatred vnto mankind, who doth not onely ſeeke like a Lion, whom to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, but alſo is alwaies tempting vs to deuoure
<note n="w" place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 5.</note> one another, as here <hi>Iezabel</hi> hath nothing to eaſe her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack withall, but blood and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge: thus we deuoure one another, as if man, who is created after the Image of God, were of no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but preſently vpon our priuat diſcontentments and grudges, to butcher them vp, as if we were Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, euen to feede vpon our brethren and to drinke vp their blood, as it were in boules.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that if any man ſtand in our way, or in our light, wee conclude him preſentlie, and either by potion, or ſome other ſiniſter practiſe, wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him dead, ſo little account doe wee make of that blood, which is ſo pretious in the eyes of God: thus wee fall one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, vpon a diſpleaſure, as <hi>Caine</hi> doth vpon <hi>Abel</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4.8.</note>,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17605:33"/>and eaſe our ſtomacks and haue our deſires, forgetting that blood muſt haue blood, and that it cries for vengeance againſt vs: this is the Diuels mallice againſt vs, who ſtirres vppe after this manner. Wilt thou endure and pocket vp theſe wronges, wilt thou bee accounted baſe minded, and wilt not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy reputation? this is rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torique, and the rule is, that the lie deſerueth the ſtabbe: that it is honourable and the tryall of an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall ſpirite to enter into ſingle combate, and their honour is their life, and theſe Maximes maketh them like fierce Tigers one againſt another, ſo cruell are wee growne, ſo dangerous the times, as that <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> caution may well bee our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation for our latter times,
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.4.</note> Take you heede euerie one of his neighbour, and truſt you not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Brother for they will vtterly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant and deſtroy one another.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>vindicta, vindicta,</hi> is our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17605:33"/>place among the common people, yea, nobler breſts haue been ſet on fire with reuenge, as if the blood and death of innocents would not as wel cry for vengeance againſt them, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt other men: but he that lookes into the booke of God finds, that the greater the offender is in this kind, the greater the puniſhment hath bin, not one of <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe ſhall bee left to make water againſt the wall, and as for <hi>Iezabel</hi> her ſelfe, the very dogs ſhall licke their lips after her blood, and be glutted with it; let this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but eſpecially the feare of the Lord temper our paſſions, &amp; ſo guide our vnderſtandings, that we giue not place vnto the diuell,
<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> in theſe ſo deadly and damnable enterprizes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>This ſerues for our animaduerſion, as concerning the condition of them that thus proceede in the degrees of finne, ſurely their iudgement ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not, but increaſeth as their ſins
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17605:34"/>are enlarged, Hell is ſaid to be enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with theſe augmentators, for they are vpon the skore, and it runs vpon the reckoning, vntill the Lord come to render vnto euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works, the mercifull Aduocate Ieſus Chriſt the righteous pleadeth the cauſes of all penitent ſinners
<note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1</note>: but theſe men in their hearts that cannot repent, heape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues wrath againſt the day of wrath, and declaration of the vengeance and iudgement of God, who, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>will render it vnto them</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.5.6.</note>. This is a fearefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: for if euery ſinne in his owne nature deſerue death, and that is the wages of it
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note>: how then ſhall theſe men anſwere the many thouſand ſins that haue been committed by them without feeling.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſhewes, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of ſuch men ſleepeth not:
<note n="d" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord will awaken vnto them, and ſuddenly come with the account:</hi> they haue beene long inthe action, but their deſtruction ſhall ſweepe them
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17605:34"/>away in a moment, and their confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be of longer continuance: for as they haue beene continuall tranſgreſſors, ſo muſt they be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually tormented with flames vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable, with horror vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, loe thus they ſtand, or rather fall, who doe not thinke our God is iuſt to recompence their wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>When they are ripe, or rather rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their ſinnes, then comes the dreadfull harueſt, they ſhall bee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as God threatneth the Amorites;
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.14</note> 
                  <hi>When they haue filled vp the meaſure of their ſinnes, then ſhall they be rooted out, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſame which was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto <hi>Amos</hi> in a Viſion,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Amos</hi> 8.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> where hee ſaw a basket of Sommer fruite, whereby is meant ripeneſſe, or the time that the fruite ſhould be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <hi>Now ſaith the Lord, the end is come, I will paſſe by this people no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this be conſidered, O yee men of earth, the God of heauen will not be mocked, and therfore be not you deceiued, whatſoeuer ſins are newly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17605:35"/>committed, doe not thinke the old ſinnes are forgotten, vnleſſe thou be a new man, then thy ſins of old ſhall not be imputed vnto thee
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.</note>: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it will goe hard againſt vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that garment of righteouſneſſe couer vs, the Lord will write bitter things againſt vs, and make vs to poſſeſſe the iniquities of our youth.
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 14.26</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Seeing the wicked grow worſe and worſe, let the righteous worke by contraries, let them grow better and better from grace to grace, from vertue to vertue. Let them proceed in goodnes,
<note place="margin">Chriſtians ought to be Graduates in godlineſſe.</note> as the other doe in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: let them bee the Lords Graduates, and proceede in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Vniuerſitie of Sion, euen in the Church of God: of this proceeding, the Propher <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in the Pſalms;
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7.</note> The righteous grow from ſtrength to ſtrength, vntill they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God in Sion, there they are to bee preſented, and there it is, that they ſhall bee eternized: let them therefore begin with godlines,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17605:35"/>and ende with golineſſe, and they ſhall not looſe their labour, for it hath the promiſes both of this life, and the life to come
<note n="k" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8</note> proceede therefore, O you Saints and ſeruants of the Lord, you feare the Lord, they that doe ſo, neede to feare nothing elſe: keepe your inheritance, it is farre beyond <hi>Naboaths</hi> Vineyard, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel</hi> ſhall not hurt you, the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt you, the Kingdome of heauen is prepared for you, and for all thoſe, that loue the comming of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, and the moſt bleſſed Spirit, one eternall, immortall, inuiſible and God onely wiſe, be praiſe and dominion with al glorious aſcription, now and for euermore. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
